have you ever thought about what null
actually means in managed languages such
as C sharp or Java if you try and use an
object that's null you'll get a null
reference or a null pointer exception
that's because there's languages
specifically Hold Your Hand
but what about C plus plus that's what
we're going to look into here today but
first what is the value of null well
over here I have some C plus code let's
go ahead and type in void point of value
and we'll set it equal to null pointer
now there's no null keyword in C plus
plus instead we use something called
null pointer if we set a breakpoint on
this line over here I'll make sure my
configuration is debug and I'll hit F5
we'll hit this breakpoint and if we
hover over a value we'll see 0x and then
a whole bunch of zeros let's look at
this value specifically in memory though
I'm going to go to debug Windows memory
and then memory one and then what I'll
do is I'll just type in Ampersand value
and hit enter this will take me to the
memory address of this actual variable
so we have a void pointer variable
stored on the stack and this is its
address and if we look at the value at
that address we see eight of these
groups of zeros that's eight bytes and
they're all set to zero why eight bytes
because I've built in a 64-bit
architecture and avoid points or any
pointer any memory address is going to
be 8 bytes okay so that's your answer
null pointer is equal to zero it's
stored as zero in memory now there is
one other keyword you may have seen in C
plus for null it's actually not a
keyword but rather a macro and it's null
with capital letters now this is mostly
used in C however it's totally
acceptable to use it in C plus as well
just might not be stylistically
appropriate if we actually go to the
definition of this macro you'll see
there's kind of two definitions here if
C plus plus is defined it's just zero
otherwise in C's case it would be zero
but explicitly cast to a void pointer no
real difference here the point is null
is defined as zero so we can just
substitute this with zero if we want
it's the same effect it just makes your
code look a little bit different and
strictly speaking probably isn't
recommended because it adds a little bit
extra complexity I guess I mean we like
writing our code in English don't we so
null probably makes more sense than
having a pointer set to zero and it's
also perfectly valid to set any integer
really to null because remember null is
just zero and this works so why wouldn't
that work especially if it is actually
defined to this zero and not to avoid
point of zero because that will cause
problems so is null really all that
scary I mean it's just an it's just an
integer defined to zero like a number
defined to zero Y is zero so scary and
why connect crash my program the problem
here comes down to pointers pointers are
just memory addresses and xero is not a
valid memory address so what happens is
you will get something called an access
violation if you try and read memory
that is not valid and it's not really
the memory specifically that's not valid
it's just what memory address the
operating system determines is not valid
so if you're trying to specifically read
a memory address that does not exist or
does not contain memory that you're
allowed to access a good kind of real
world analogy to this is if you type in
an address into Google Maps that just
physically does not exist like you're
just not you can't go there so how does
all of this work with objects well let's
create a class here called entity
I'm just going to give it a default
Constructor
and two private variables maybe a parent
entity
and a name
now because I want to access the name
I'm also going to go ahead and add a
getter for that
so const a city string reference get
name const return
M name and I'm also going to write one
more function here called print type
which is just going to print the type of
the class which is just entity so I'm
going to go ahead and type in acid C out
entity okay so I have an NC class with a
couple member variables and a couple of
functions cool so how would I create
this class in C plus plus well if we
want to strictly kind of compare this to
manage languages like C sharp and Java
you'd have to create it on the Heap so
we can type in NC and C equals new
entity this is equivalent to the kind of
C sharp or Java way of creating this
which would be like that of course this
is C plus plus so it would actually be
preferable to try and create it on the
stack unless you specifically needed to
be on the Heap however we'll just ignore
that for now especially because we're
talking about null so what happens if we
just don't set a value for it so if I
just type in entity pointer entity like
this what's going to happen well if I
try and use something like get name and
I want to print that out
if I run this program I'm actually not
even going to be able to run this
program I'm going to get a build error
and it's going to tell me that I'm
trying to use an uninitialized local
variable entity and so what I need to do
is explicitly set a value to it so let's
go ahead and just set it to something
like null pointer hit F5 and we'll see
what happens okay we get a read access
violation this was eight
now why does it say this
was Ace we'll get back to that if we
look at our call stack and we go back to
the main function I'll close this memory
view if we scroll down a little bit we
can see that this line of code that
crashed entity is null so even though
the actual kind of Crash we got is
somewhere inside like STD string if we
go back to our code you can see that the
reason this crashed in the first place
was because this was null that's a
really important thing to remember when
you're debugging this if you have access
violations go back to your code and see
what it is you're trying to access and
what the value actually is if we try and
run this in the release configuration
we'll get something slightly different
it's going to tell us that we have an
access violation reading location 20
over here and you can see in this case
the debugger actually breaks right on
this line that's because it's optimized
a few things and get name probably
doesn't even exist anymore but the point
is we're going to get crashes they're
going to be either access violation or
read access violation debug gives us a
little bit more information tells us
what the value of this is but but
overall we know that it's not working in
managed languages this would be much
easier to debug because it would just
tell us that entity is null whereas in C
plus plus depending on your compiler
depending on a few other things it's a
little bit more cryptic usually Okay so
we've determined that get name on NST
which is a null pointer clearly doesn't
work because you can't call a function
on a null pointer that doesn't really
make sense does it now we do have one
other function print type so what do you
think happens if we call that if I just
call entity print type and entity is
null what's going to happen now while
you think about it let me tell you about
brilliant the sponsor of this video if
you haven't heard of brilliant before
you're seriously missing out brilliant
is an amazing website filled with many
many courses on various stem topics math
and computer science go together really
really well and Brilliant have a lot of
really high quality courses on both of
those topics whether you're just
starting to realize the importance of
math and want to get started with
something easy or you're trying to learn
some more advanced math perhaps for 3D
graphics brilliant have got you covered
and if it's specifically computer
science you're interested in maybe you
want to learn more about neural networks
they are one of the best places to check
out for that because all of their
courses are extremely interactive and
engaging they have these beautiful
widgets that you can play with to make
sure that you visually understand what's
going on and they'll also continually
quiz you to make sure that you're
actually learning and retaining the
information and guess what you can get
started for free just go to
brilliant.org the channel check it out
for yourself just scroll through their
courses see if you find something to eat
like it's free there's no reason not to
do it and if you do find a bunch of
courses that you like and want to spend
more time on the platform brilliant have
been nice enough to offer the first 200
of my subscribers 20 off an annual
membership huge thank you as always to
brilliant for sponsoring this video okay
well entity print type it's null let's
go ahead and run this code I want to
stop it right here though I'll hit F5
and whoop well I don't see any access
violation let's take a look at our
console and
check this out it printed entity so it
did exactly what the function said and
if I just hit F10 okay now I get an
access violation so what seems to be
happening is if I just comment out this
line for a minute I'll remove all my
breakpoints I'll hit F5 my program runs
successfully unlike in managed languages
where you would get a null pointer or a
null reference exception so how come
this works but this doesn't work and
does this even make sense that this
works I mean this is this object is null
so what is it calling print type on that
doesn't make any sense well let's scroll
up a little bit and talk about how
methods actually work these are
functions within a class they're not
static functions or anything like that
they're member functions we usually call
them methods in object oriented
programming I usually just call them
functions or member functions though
between you and me so when the compiler
is compiling this program and it's
looking at this class what actually
happens to this class how do these
classes work well if you actually think
back to C then there's no such thing as
a class there is a struct which is kind
of the same thing however structs cannot
have functions inside them so let's talk
about how we would go about rewriting
this class in C well we'd go down here
we'd create a struct called NC I want to
call it data just so that it's a
different name I'm going to copy these
two members so we can have a structure
of different variables that's fine I'll
just change this to be entity data so
we're pointing to our same type here and
then how would we get these functions to
work well we just write them outside of
the class right so I'll copy them over
here I'll get rid of this const and
maybe I'll just add a little leading
entity over here just so that we know
that it's kind of supposed to be a
function of this particular class even
though it's just a free floating
function of course okay cool well the
first problem is we have to return name
but name is obviously relative to a
particular instance of this struct so
what do we do well we need to actually
take in that struct as a parameter this
is exactly what happens in C plus plus
when we actually compile this class the
methods inside the class the functions
inside the class get converted integers
regular free floating functions that
actually take in an instance of the
class as the their first parameter and
guess what that instance is called this
now in this case we can't name it this
because that's the reserved keyword so
let's just go ahead and name itself and
then M name obviously comes from self so
now this makes sense because M name is
coming from this particular instance we
actually now have a way to get that
specific data we want to return now one
minor addition here the original
function was actually labeled as const
which means that the self that gets
taken in here the this pointer that gets
taken in is actually a const pointer
like this and with print type the exact
same thing happens now print type is not
marked as const so what would happen is
we take in this obviously but it's not
going to be const and just for example's
sake if print type had been a static
function like this then it just wouldn't
take in the instance that's why you can
never access a member such as M parent
or something like that from within a
static function you can't do that
because a non-stack member reference
must be relative to a specific object
and if we don't take in a specific
object in the first place then of course
we can't possibly access the data unless
it is also static because in that case
it knows where the data lives so back to
our normal example so what happens if we
try and call get name but entity is null
well it means that the self that is
passed in here is
now
and what are we trying to do we're
trying to specifically access a string
from null right this is zero we're
trying to access its name and return it
as an actual string reference which
means that we're going to read that
memory address a memory address that is
invalid and thus we crash now let's
scroll down to this function do you see
the difference here
okay we also call entity print type and
C is in fact null pointer so self is
null but then like what do we do here we
just print out the word entity followed
by a new line do we access self at all
no we don't we don't care about self at
all this may as well be like a static
function because we don't even use self
or the this pointer so that is why this
doesn't crash because it's not the fact
that you're actually calling a function
on null that's perfectly valid because
remember it's not like this function
exists within the actual entity class
it's not physically existing inside here
it gets compiled out into something like
this by the compiler it's just a normal
function inside our compiled binary
there's just a bunch of CPU instructions
there's just a bunch of machine code at
a particular address inside that binary
that gets loaded up into memory and the
instruction pointer will simply jump to
that address and start executing
instructions it's not like it magically
lives inside that object and if the
object is null it's not going to work so
the thing that causes the crash is the
fact that we're actually trying to use
these member variables and they can't be
accessed because the object itself the
instance is null and to further
demonstrate this case let's talk about a
little something let's talk about a
macro called offset of now offset of is
a pretty cool macro what it will do is
it lets you pass in the name of a class
such as entity I might just use entity
data here but it's the same thing and
then the name of a member variable such
as M name and what it will do
is it will actually give you the offset
of that particular member in memory so
if I bring this code down over here
offset of M name and we print that
offset let's hit F5 you can see the
offset of M name is eight so we can use
this macro to actually tell us what the
offset of this is in memory why is it
eight because this because this am
parent variable is obviously the very
first thing in the struct so it's going
to be at an offset of zero and then what
is its size well it's a pointer on a
64-bit architecture so it's going to be
eight bytes which puts M name at an
offset of eight meaning the first zero
through seven inclusive bytes are
occupied by this variable and then the
next however many buys her string takes
from byte 8 onwards is occupied by this
variable but how does offset of know
that how exactly does it work well if we
actually go to the definition of it
there's a couple different definitions
depending on again whether or not this C
plus plus macro is defined but both of
them will technically work in C plus
plus we're going to look at the bottom
one just because it's a little bit more
concise you can see what it's doing and
it's pretty simple we take in two
variables here S and M now s is entity
data and M is mname so this is entity
data what we're doing is we're basically
casting zero to be an entity data
pointer then we're going to that member
variable getting the memory address of
it and casting that to a size T so if we
were to write this ourselves then offset
would be equal to entity data pointer 0
right so this is step one so this is a
null pointer and you can actually use
null pointer if you want it's the same
thing and relative to that null pointer
we're actually looking up that specific
member variable the specific member
variable that caused a crash earlier but
how come this is working well the
crucial difference is that we're not
actually looking at the value of it
we're not trying to read the memory at
this address because that would be a
rate access violation what we're doing
is we're actually getting the memory
address of that variable so in other
words where is this located in memory
and since it's relative to zero then
that gives us the offset if it was
relative to an actual entity data
allocation so if we actually created a
new entity data here and then we tried
to look at name of course that would be
relative to whatever address this
actually gets allocated at but since we
are specifically looking at it from this
kind of zero pointer it means that this
will in fact just be the offset and then
the final step is to cast this which is
going to be a string pointer because
Eminem is a string we can just pass that
to something like a un64t or a size t as
the macro was doing and that gives us
our offset if we try and run this
program we will of course get the exact
same result and if we try and run up
with null pointer then of course we'll
also get the same result and if we
actually take this breakpoint away so
that it tries to run this invalid code
as we did earlier in the video and it
said that this was eight you can now see
what the problem is that string is
located at an offset of eight bytes so
the value that it gets is eight and it
tries to read from that specific value
and that of course is wrong so again
it's not the fact that this specific
self is null here when it tries to
actually return the name it's the fact
that we're then trying to print it which
means it has to access the string which
means when it asks the string phrase
address it is going to be at an offset
of eight to entity and then C is null so
zero plus eight gives us eight and we
get a little message and we get a little
message telling us that this was 8 which
is a rate access violation we can't read
from that memory address because that's
not valid memory and that is what null
is hopefully this video is helped
helpful to you guys if you liked it
please don't forget to hit the like
button below if you have other
suggestions for Sleepless videos leave
them in the comments below don't forget
to check out brilliant.org the channel
and I will see you guys next time
goodbye